A Guide to the Papers of Thomas Jefferson and the Randolph Family, 1784-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 2: Papers of the Randolph Family
  - Paul Leicester Ford to [Sarah Nicholas] Randolph, 1892 January 22, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:59)
    Concerning a genealogy of the Jefferson family including a description of two Thomas Jeffersons, and asking questions about the will of Peter Jefferson's father.
  - Maria J. C. Mason to Patty Taylor, 1892 November 2, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:60)
    Describing her loneliness and lack of correspondents in the family.
  - Reverend J. R. Taylor to unidentified niece, 1896 April 8, ALS (Box-folder 1:60a)
    Includes a clipping dated 1897 March 21 of a sermon delivered at St. Andrew's Episcopal Church, Bryan, Texas.
  - Harmon and Walsh, Attorneys at Law to Reverend J. R. Taylor and Newspaper clipping concerning Vinegar Hill, 1909 April 6 and 1956 February 28, ALS copy, 1 p.; with original envelope addressed to Miss Cornelia J. Taylor; Postmarked Accomac, June 1909; With additional newspaper clipping. (Box-folder 1:61)
    In response to Reverend J. R. Taylor's inquiry about purchasing some land near Vinegar Hill in Charlottesville. The newspaper clipping contains an article on the history of Vinegar Hill.
  - List of Inventions by Thomas Jefferson Still in Use in 1918 by Fanny M. Burke, 1918 September 4, ANS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:62)
    With an additional note that Jefferson's gold medal award for inventing "Mouldboard or plowshare" is in the possession of her brothers.
  - M. N. to Jane Hollins Nicholas Randolph, n.y. February 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with address; Postmarked Baltimore, MD, February 26. (Box-folder 1:63)
    Concerning Sarah's illness and plans to take her back to the doctor. Tells her of "a total reform of D. C. [who] has joined the teetotal temperance society [and who] is [now] at home every day to dinner." Asks for her prayers that this is a lasting reform, but their "ma not knowing the necessity for it, looks upon his having joined the society a great nonsense." Desires strict instruction for his child in school, and provides his thoughts on strict education, and sends his best wishes to family members.
  - E. L. Harrison to Patty Taylor, n.y. May 4, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:64)
    Tells her to tend to her body, and reminds her of a relative, Sarah, whose death resulted from neglecting hers. Provides a detailed account of Sarah's last days, and tells news of family and personal acquaintances.
  - Sue Blackburn to Aunt Jane [Hollins Nicholas Randolph,] n.y. September 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:65)
    Concerning grieving for "dear Bennett," and mentions visitors there or expected in Washington. In a postscript, she asks if the Taylor boys are out of the Army, because "she feel[s] like crying over the sufferings of our private soldiers."
  - [Sue Blackburn] to Dearest Jane [Hollins Nicholas Randolph], n.d., ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:66)
    Concerning hiring a new cook, her boarder Edward Stribling, and family illnesses.
  - Wilson Miles Cary to S[arah] N[icholas] Randolph, n.d., ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:67)
    A note on Thomas Jefferson's sister Elizabeth who died 1773 January 1. Cary continues, "I have always understood that she was very feeble minded if not an idiot. & that she and her maid were drowned together while attempting to cross the Rivanna in a skiff."
  - B[ernard] Peyton to Caroline Randolph, n.d., ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with address on verso. (Box-folder 1:68)
    Discusses her preparations in a new home, and worries that she will not have the house ready when her family arrives in two months. Relates her intentions to travel to Philadelphia, and a visit from the Carrs.
  - Diagram of Monticello by [Cornelia J. Randolph], n.d., Diagram of Monticello with a description of furniture, and detailing the location of the furniture in the house. (Box-folder 1:69)
  - Sarah Randolph to Mr. Harris, n.d., AL, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:70)
    Concerning sending him a copy of a book she edited, The Domestic Life of Jefferson, and the appropriation of five thousand dollars for the restoration of the tomb of Thomas Jefferson. She would like the restoration to be carried out in accordance with Jefferson's desires, although she would like the obelisk to be slightly taller than the proportions he set down.
  - Recollections of Thomas Jefferson by Thomas Jefferson Randolph, n.d., TMs typescript copy, 14 pp. on 14 l. (Box-folder 1:71)
    Concerning his intimacy with Thomas Jefferson, Jefferson's disposition, views on decorum and decency, morality, conversation, and religion. Contains a long description of the scene at Jefferson's death, and Thomas Jefferson's desire for an understated funeral. Additionally, provides a rough sketch of a typical day for Thomas Jefferson, his aversion to hard spirits. Provides an anecdote about the only exception to Jefferson's gentle disposition, for "the only impatience of temper he ever exhibited was with his horse." Also mentions his early financial success and his subsequent debt.
  - Caryanne Ramsey Ruffin to Caroline Ramsey Randolph, n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:72)
    Concerning the affairs and health of her children, her illness and the possibility of a necessary visit to Dr. Buckley.
  - Drawings and Photograph of Lego, Home of the J. C. R. Taylor Family by Patty Taylor, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:73)
    One drawing from the side, one from the front; Two technical drawings of the interior of the building, and one photograph of Lego from the side.
  - Miscellaneous, n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 1:74)
    A printed copy of Susan Coolidge's poem, Little Kindnesses, a manuscript copy of Here and There, a recipe for Strawberry Charlotte, and a typed fragment of a Jefferson biography.
  - Newspaper Notices of Death of Various Jefferson Descendents, n.d., 5 items; With photocopies. (Box-folder 1:75)
    Newspaper clippings concerning the deaths of various Jefferson descendents. Two concern the death of Ellen Wayles Harrison, one concerning the death of Maria Jefferson Carr Mason, one concerning the death of Major Thomas Jefferson Randolph, and one concerning the death of Carolina R. Randolph.
  - Printed note regarding Early Entrance Requirements and Fees of the University of Virginia, n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 1:76)